是, 大臣  第3季第3集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:英吉沙 tpring 校对:tpring
家丑外扬
第7项 第7项是什么?
Item 7. What is item 7?
请允许我重申一遍 大臣
Well, if I may just recapitulate...
抱歉 大臣
Sorry, Minister.
您还没说的议程是不能重申的
You can't actually recapitulate an item if you haven't started it yet.
多谢 伯纳 没你我们可完了 我接着说?
Thank you. Where would we be without you? May I continue?
重申一遍上次会议 会议纪要
Recapitulating on our last meeting and the minutes,
您当然收到了?      当然 对对
which you doubtless received... Doubtless, yes, yes.
什么纪要 汉弗莱?
Er... what minutes, Humphrey?
对南德贝郡政府进行纪律处分的提案
Disciplinary action against the South Derbyshire local authority.
啊 对...提醒我一下好吗 伯纳?
Ah, yes... Will you remind me, Bernard?
他们没完成法定报表
They failed to complete their statutory returns
也没上交统计资料
and supply us with statistical information.
对了 我们怎么办?      怎么处分?
What'll we do? The action we can take?
大臣出面指责
A rebuke from the minister,
发表声明宣布他们玩忽职守
press statement about their incompetence,
扣发补贴 以及最终手段 您知道的
the withholding of grants or ultimately, as you are fully aware...
是 当然知道
Yes, of course.
好
Good.
什么我知道的?
I'm fully aware of what?
什么?      我知道什么?
What? What am I fully aware of?
我还真不知道      你说的 最终手段
I mean... You said, ultimately, as I am fully...
最终手段 把郡政府告上法庭 抱歉
Ultimately, taking the local authority to court. Sorry.
有这么严重吗?
Is it that serious?
严重? 这是灭顶之灾      为什么?
Serious? it抯 catastrophic! Why?
如果地方政府都不按要求交报表
If local authorities don't send us statistics,
政府数据就纯属胡说了      怎么?
government figures will be a nonsense.
不完整啊      政府数据本来就是胡说
They'll be incomplete. Government figures are a nonsense.
大概汉弗莱爵士想确认
I think Sir Humphrey wants to ensure
它们是纯的胡说
they're a complete nonsense.
我是说...
I mean... er...
干吗拿南德贝开刀?
Why should we make an example of South Derbyshire?
您干吗反对 那个郡议会归您的党派管?
Do you object because the council抯 controlled by your party?
没有没有
Oh, no, no, no.
绝对没有 不过不能找个反对党的选区么?
No, no, no. But couldn抰 we just... pick on an opposition council?
大臣      南德贝真有那么糟?
Oh, Minister! Is South Derbyshire all that bad?
惨不忍睹 他们不交蓝表格
Terrible! They won't return their blue forms!
去年的就业率问卷也没搞完
They haven't completed employment trends questionnaire!
少数民族统计征询表是手写的
ethnic personnel breakdown request in longhand
还写在部门公函背面
on the back of a departmental circular!
社工修订分析表两个季度没交
We haven't had their social analysis for two quarters
还有资料处理量化表
or their data-processing appropriation tables!
真没想法了 坏透了
They're unbelievable! Really evil!
怎么 就因为少交几套表?
What, because they won't return their forms in triplicate?
对哦 真不知德贝人怎么活
I don't see how life can go on in Derbyshire!
正是 大臣
Exactly, Minister.
真是无能到登峰造极了
They really are in a class of their own for incompetence.
没一点成就吗?      有趣的是...
Have they no redeeming features? It is fascinating...
没问题的话 大臣 我们直接下处分了
If that's all right, we can take coercive action.
大臣可能...      您同意了 大臣?
The minister might like to know... You approve?
不好下手 他们是朋友
Yes, it抯 a difficult one. They're friends.
他们不是优秀政府的朋友
They are no friends of good administration.
好 给我24小时
Well, give me 24 hours.
我去党内协调一下
I'll have to square the party organisation.
让党主席受邀
Get the chairman invited
去10号里喝个小酒
to one of those drinky-do's at Number 10.
缓冲一下 还有事吗?
Soften the blow. Right, anything else?
没有 似乎都完成了
No, I think that seems to be all.
理查 我有事要请教 有空吗?     当然
Richard, I need your advice, if you can spare a moment.
伯纳 我不太乐意
Bernard, I'm not happy about...
处分南德贝
disciplining South Derbyshire.
怎么了 大臣?      直觉
Why not, Minister? Instinct.
卡赖特博士似乎想告诉我什么
Dr Cartwright seemed to be trying to tell me something.
我想去看看他
I think I'll drop in on him.
还是别去吧 大臣      怎么?
I wouldn't do that. Why not?
一般大臣想知道什么 要叫人呈上来
If ministers want to know will be brought to their notice.
要是他们自己去打听 没准会...
If they go out looking for information, they might...
打听出来?      对
Find it? Yes.
汉弗莱爵士很反感大臣到处串门
Sir Humphrey does not like ministers dropping in on people.
他管这叫"乱逛"      女皇也串门
Gong walkabout, he calls it. The Queen does it.
她不会进副秘书的门
She doesn't drop in on Under-Secretaries,
汉弗莱爵士的部门里不会
not in Sir Humphrey's department.
他在几号房?      我提出严正反对 大臣
What's his room number? I must advise you against this.
反对收到      4017号
Advice noted. Room 4017.
往下一层 左手第二走廊
Down one flight, second corridor on the left.
要是我48小时回不来 派搜索队来
If I'm not back in 48 hours, send out a search party!
你好 格拉汉 我是伯纳
Hello, Graham, it抯 Bernard.
告诉汉弗莱爵士 大臣刚出去乱逛了
Tell Sir Humphrey that the Minister抯 just gone walkabout.
对对 擅离职守
Yes, yes, AWOL.
我当然跟他说了 对
Well, of course I told him, yes.
我知道 你最好马上通知他
I know. I think you'd better let him know right away.
1 2 3 4 5
One... two... three... four... five...
6 7 8 9 10
six... seven... eight... nine... ten.
怎么搞的?
What's all this about?
大臣刚出了办公室而已
The minister抯 just left the office, that's all.
而已? 你说他跑到楼里去了?
That's all? Do you mean he's loose in the building?
怎么不通知我?
Why didn抰 you warn me?
我劝他别去 可他是大臣
I did advise him, but he is the minister.
没有禁止大臣接触下属的规定
There's no prohibition against ministers talking to their staff.
他找谁谈话 伯纳?      也许他只是心烦
Who's he talking to? Perhaps he was just restless.
如果大臣心烦 伯纳
If the minister抯 restless,
他可以去公园里喂鸭子
he can feed the ducks in St James's Park!
是 汉弗莱爵士
Yes, Sir Humphrey.
说吧 大臣在找谁谈话?
Tell me who the minister抯 talking to.
当然大臣想找谁都行吧
Well, surely the minister can talk to anyone.
伯纳 我正在写你的年度工作报告
Bernard... I'm in the middle of writing your annual report.
这项职责
Now, it is not a responsibility
你我都不希望我在完成期间
that either of us would wish me to discharge
心情不佳吧
whilst I am in a bad temper.
大臣在找谁谈话?
Who's the minister talking to?
也许您能指教我 汉弗莱爵士
Perhaps you could help me.
如果他是找外人 您当然得知道
I can see that you should know if he calls on an outsider.
但我不明白为什么要通知您
I fall to see why you should be informed
如果他只想...假如说
if he just wants to, to take a hypothetical example,
只想问卡赖特博士...
to... check a point with... Dr Cartwright...
谢了 伯纳 失陪了
Thank you, Bernard. Must fly.
4017房间      我知道
Room 4017. I know.
他们说的南德贝的事 是真的吗?
Are those things about South Derbyshire true?
我估计可能吧      这话怎讲?
They may be. What are you saying?
我只说南德贝郡是
I'm saying that South Derbyshire is
全国最高效的地方政府
the most efficient local authority in the UK.
最高效? 还要我把他们当最差的处分
I'm meant to tick them off for being the least.
看看数据
Look at the figures.
不是没上报吗?      没有
I thought they didn抰 send us any. No.
可他们自己记录得很好 就这些
But they keep their own records perfectly well. I'm gong on those.
全中部数他们失职率最低
They've got the lowest truancy record in the Midlands.
市政委员会行政开销最低
The lowest admin cost per council house.
人员编制与个人收入比值最低
The lowest ratio of council workers to rate income.
环境最好 卫生官员最少
The lowest number of environmental health officers.
什么卫生官员?      抓耗子的
What are those officers? Rat-catchers.
基本上所有儿童都能读写
Virtually all children can read and write,
虽然搞的是素质教育
even though they've had a progressive education.
对了 他们的社会福利人员
They've got the smallest establishment
在全国也是最少的
of social workers in the UK.
这是好事吗?      对 说明效率高
Is that supposed to be a good thing? Oh, yes. Sign of efficiency.
社工循环递增率 您看
Parkinson抯 Law of Social Work, you see.
就是说社会问题一增加
Social problems increase to occupy
社工也得全员出动 顾不上别的了
the number of social workers available to deal with them.
数据都对吗?      对的 我保证
And all these figures are Ok? Yes, I assure you.
理查 我正想...
Richard, I wonder if I...
是您呀 大臣
Good heavens, Minister.
汉弗莱 真巧啊      无巧不成书啊
Humphrey, what a coincidence. Yes, indeed, what a surprise!
对      对
Yes. Yes.
我正好...路过
I was just... passing.
路过?      对 路过
Passing? Yes, passing.
路过啊 您要去哪呢?
Oh, passing. And where were you gong?
我只是在...过路而已
I was just gong... past.
路过门口 卡赖特...理查门口
Past the door. Cartwright抯... Richard抯 door.
突然我就想 "咦...?"
And I thought..."Hello..."
还想了别的吗?
Did you think anything further?
我想 "都到门口了 何不打开门瞧瞧?"
Yes, I thought, "Why should I pass the door? Why not open it?"
思路不错 大臣 门就是干这个用的
Good thinking, that's what doors are for.
对
Right.
我刚好有些问题要澄清
There were some points I wanted to clear up.
好好 什么问题?
Oh, good, good. What points?
都是些小问题      小问题
Just a couple of odd points. Couple of odd points.
有多小?      其实也没多小
How odd? Oh... not all that odd.
就开了个会     能跟您说句话吗 大臣?
We just had a meeting. Could I have a word with you?
当然可以 等我...      我说现在
Yes, of course, as soon as... No, I mean now.
好 说吧      不 上楼去您办公室
All right, carry on. No, upstairs in your office.
理查肯定不介意      不 上楼去 大臣
I'm sure Richard doesn't mind. No, upstairs.
卡赖特博士也不差这几分钟吧
I'm sure that Dr Cartwright can spare you for a few moments.
谢谢 理查 大臣您请
Thank you, Richard. Minister.
你先出去 伯纳
You may go, Bernard.
大臣 您这是要干什么?
Minister, what was all that in aid of?
我听到些有趣的事实
I have learnt some interesting facts.
我衷心希望您下不为例      你说什么?
I hope it does not happen again. I beg your pardon?
您不能到处跟部里的人说话
You cannot speak to people in the department.
怎么不能?
Why not?
我不知他们说了什么 怎么给您提建议?
How can I advise you if I don't know what抯 said?
我必须掌握情况
I must know what is gong on.
您就是不能私下跟人谈话
You cannot have private conversations!
万一他们说的是假话呢?
You may be told things that are not true!
那你纠正嘛      万一是真话呢?
You can put me right. But they may be true!
不完全假 但有偏向 会误导您
Not entirely false, but misleading, open to misinterpretation.
我看你有事瞒着我      绝对没有 大臣
You're trying to keep things from me. Absolutely not, Minister.
要做好记录 要留下档案
Minutes must be taken, records must be kept.
您不会永远在这 我们也不会
You won't be here forever, Nor will we.
几年之后
in years to come...
要知道您说过什么 若卡赖特明天调走
If Cartwright were moved tomorrow,
信息要怎么核实?
how could we check information?
卡赖特明天不会调走      哦 是吗?
Cartwright won't be moved tomorrow. Oh, really?
邮报的安德鲁来找您 大臣
Alex Andrews from the Mall to see you.
且慢 伯纳 给我记到档案里
Ah, hang on. I'd like you to minute this.
什么都得归档 是吧
Everything must be minuted, you know.
坐下好吗 汉弗莱?
Sit down, won't you, Humphrey?
南德贝郡政府      等我记一下
Now South Derbyshire Council... Just a minute.
我是这么说的 南德贝郡政府
Yes, that's what I said. South Derbyshire.
卡赖特博士说那是全国最高效的
Dr Cartwright said it is the most efficient council in Britain.
他说低效吧      高效 汉弗莱
Inefficient, I think he means. Efficient, Humphrey.
经济实惠
Economical, effective.
只不过不想往白厅送报表而已
Just not interested in sending bits of blue paper to Whitehall.
可他们非送不可      为什么?
But they have to send them. Why?
法律要求的      他们不送 英国照样运转
It is a statutory requirement. And if they don't, Britain carries on.
南德贝照样运转
South Derbyshire carries on.
可如果他们不上报信息
But if they don't send us the information,
计划 批复申请
the plans and the requests for permission,
那还要我们干吗?
what are we here for?
问得好 要我们干吗?
Good question. What are we here for?
我们收集信息 审查计划 决定批不批申请
To collect information withhold or grant permission.
不然呢?      抱歉 大臣 我不明白
And if we didn抰? I'm sorry, Minister, I don't understand.
没有我们 也没这些事 那又如何?
If we weren't here and we didn抰 do it, what then?
对不起 大臣 我搞糊涂了
I'm sorry, you've lost me.
你的问题是 你只管手续 不看结果
You're concerned more with means than ends.
行政中没有结果 大臣 有也是恶果
There are no ends in administration, Minister, except loose ends.
行政代代相传
Administration is eternal!
永世长存      阿门
Forever and ever. Amen!
因为没结果 才有人说政府是个圈
Because there are no ends, they talk about government circles.
没错 伯纳 我们就在里头绕
Exactly, Bernard, which is what we抮e gong round in!
反正我不处分南德贝 会出洋相的
I won't discipline South Derbyshire. I'd look a complete idiot.
抱歉 大臣 这是您的工作
I'm sorry, Minister, but it抯 your job.
是说处分南德贝 您没有选择
To discipline South Derbyshire. You have no alternative.
财政部和内阁办公室一致要求
The Treasury and the Cabinet Office insist.
汉弗莱 我不同意 反正今天不行
I cannot agree to this. Not today, anyhow.
那就明天      不行 汉弗莱
Tomorrow, then. No!
抱歉 大臣 您好像没明白
I'm sorry, you don't seem to understand.
这由不得你我 这是法律
It is not up to you or to me. It is the law.
大臣 您该见邮报的人了      很好
I think you ought to talk to the Mall. Very well.
多谢 汉弗莱      多谢 大臣
Thank you, Humphrey. Thank you, Minister.
伯纳 伯纳      什么 大臣?
Bernard. Bernard. Yes, Minister?
汉弗莱怎么知道我去找卡赖特?
How did Sir Humphrey know I was with Dr Cartwright?
神的行事很难捉摸
God moves in a mysterious way.
我们搞清楚 汉弗莱不是神 好吗?
Let me make one thing perfectly clear. Humphrey is not God, Ok?
您去告诉他还是我来?
Will you tell him or shall I?
现在告诉我 他怎么知道的
Now, tell me how he knew where I was.
大臣 您对我说的话都绝对保密
Confidentially, everything you tell me Is in complete confidence
反过来 您当然也赞同
so equally, and I'm sure you appreciate this,
这个赞同不是赞同
and, by appreciate, I don't mean appreciate,
而是理解 汉弗莱爵士对我说的
I mean understand, that everything Sir Humphrey tells me
同样完全保密
Is also in confidence,
我对您说的要保密 我对汉弗莱爵士说的
as indeed everything I tell you and everything I tell Sir Humphrey
也完全保密
Is in complete confidence.
所以呢?
So?
所以秘密说来 我相信您完全理解
So, in confidence, I am confident you understand
我为汉弗莱爵士保密 为您保密
that for me to keep Sir Humphrey's confidence,
因此他和我的谈话
conversations between him and me
必须保密 就像您和我的谈话
must as confidential as conversations between you and me
完全保密 还是请安德鲁进来吧
are completely confidential.
安德鲁先生 大臣      谢谢 伯纳
Mr Andrews, Minister. Thank you, Bernard.
啊 艾利 你好吗?      你好 吉姆
Ah, Alex. Hello, Jim.
请坐      谢谢
Sit down. Thank you.
找我什么事?      需要你帮忙
What can I do for you? I need your help.
我在写一件奇谈
I've come across a fascinating story.
你知不知道你的政府
Do you realise that your government
正要拱手将价值4千万的
Is about to hand over 40 million-worth
住宅 建筑 港口和一个小机场
of housing, building, harbour Installations and an airstrip
白送给私营开发商?
to a private developer for nothing?
4千万 逗我玩吧?      凭童子军的荣誉担保
40 million? You're having me on! No, Scout's honour.
干吗找我 不是我干的吧?      不是
Why tell me? I didn抰 do it, did I? No.
这事说来话长
It goes back a long way.
30年前 国防部在苏格兰小岛租了块地
30 years ago, the Defence had a lease on a Scottish Island.
建了兵营 哨位 司令部 海港 机场
They put up billets, HQ block, the harbour, the airstrip.
现在租约到期了 地要还给原主人
And now the lease has expired, It reverts to the original owner.
他要开个度假村
He's opening up a holiday camp.
游艇码头 小别墅 员工宿舍
Yachting marinas, chalets, staff quarters.
都是现成的 他要发了
It's all there. He'll make a fortune.
不会吧 法律...      不 那是英格兰法
He can't do that. The law... No, that's English law.
这个合同遵循苏格兰法
This contract was made under Scottish law.
有个笨蛋没看出区别
Some idiot didn抰 realise the difference.
没我们事      啊 对
We're in the clear. Ah, yes.
邮报也不能把50年代的事怪到你头上
Even the Mall can't blame you For a cock-up in the early'50s.
这倒新鲜
Makes a change.
你找我干吗? 故事你都有了
What do you want from me? You've got your story.
迟到30年 新闻总是这么及时
30 years late. As quick with the news as ever!
对英国报界算不错啦
Still, not bad for Fleet Street!
对 明天见报
We're running it tomorrow,
可主编要我做个专题
but my editor wants me to do a feature,
查清原委 翻翻文件
find out how it happened, go through the files.
为什么?      前车之鉴啊
Why? There could be lessons for today.
也许还能挖出责任人
We might find out who is responsible.
有关系吗? 起草的一定是个小职员
Does it matter? It would抳e been handled by quite a junior official.
对 那是30年前 今天他可能身居高位
30 years ago. Today he could be in an important position.
没准是个大部门的常任秘书
He could be a Permanent Secretary running a great department,
手握几十亿磅公款
responsible for spending billons of pounds of public money.
应该不会      对 可我能看文件吧?
Pretty unlikely. Yes. But can I see the papers?
当然 我不能就这么给你
Of course, I can't just hand files over.
不过你说是30年的租约?
Didn抰 you say It was a 30-year lease?
过几星期你可以去找档案公署
You can get them from the Public Records Office
按30年解密规则
under the 30-yearrule.
对 我料你会这么说
Yes, I thought you'd say that,
但你得保证我能全部拿到
but I want a guarantee that I will get all of them.
国防部文件啊      得了 这又不是机密
Well, Defence papers... Come on, this is not top security.
听着 你竞选宣言里承诺
You made a manifesto commitment
你会告诉选民真相 考验来了
saying you'd tell voters the facts. This is a test case.
我要你保证
I want your guarantee
解密前所有资料原封不动
that no papers will be removed from the file before it抯 opened.
那是当然 有我在没人会搞鬼
I don't see why not. No skin off my nose.
这是承诺吗?      当然
Is that a promise?
真的承诺 不是竞选宣言里那种
A real promise, not the sort you put in your manifesto!
你就这毛病 别人答应你反而不信
The problem with you is you won't take yes for an answer!
不然我们就写 "大臣出尔反尔"
Otherwise we do the feature about ministers ratting on manifestos.
"政府玩忽职守 开发商大发横财"
"Developers' multimillion bonanza from Goverment error"
就这些 汉弗莱?
Is that the lot, Humphrey?
抱歉 似乎就这些了 大臣 谢谢
Oh, I'm sorry. That seems to be all, Minister, thank you.
对了 汉弗莱 你看了今早的邮报没有?
Did you see that story in the Mall this morning?
苏格兰海岛丑闻      我不记得
About the Scottish Island scandal. I'm not sure.
有人犯了个错
About some cock-up somebody made
30年前订错了租约
30 years ago about the terms of the lease.
似乎是有这么一篇
I believe I did glance at it.
4千万资产流失啊 这人可惨了
40 million down the tube! Somebody really boobed there!
不是你的部门吧      当然不是
It didn抰 happen in your department? Absolutely not.
真想知道是谁      我们永远不会知道了
I wonder who it was. That is something we shall never know.
档案里会有吧?
It'll be on the files.
事事都得归档 你总说的
Everything must be put in writing, as you always say.
对 准有那么一份 可查起来就难了
Well... somewhere, no doubt, but it would take ages to search.
没人会费那个劲
Not worth anyone's time.
这你错了 邮报想做个大专题
You may be wrong. The Mall want to do a big feature.
只等档案照30年规则解密 就几个星期
Papers are released under the 30-yearrule in a few weeks.
我承诺让他们随便查
I promised them a free run of all the files.
大臣      这没关系吧
Minister! it抯 all right, isn抰 it?
没关系? 关系重大啊
All right? It most certainly is not all right!
怎么不行      这不可能 不可思议
Why on earth not? it抯 impossible, it抯 unthinkable!
为什么?      这是最高机密
Why? it抯 top security!
几间营房?      秘密海军设施
A few barracks? Secret naval installations!
反潜艇系统 低空雷达站
Anti-submarine systems! Low-level radar towers!
你又不知道
You don't know that.
不...可海军基地里就有这些东西
That's the sort of thing those bases have.
会拆除的啊      档案里会提到
But they'd have been dismantled. The papers will have references!
老皇历了      我们得申请许可
Ancient history. We need to get clearances.
谁的许可?
Who from?
安全部门 军情五处 军情六处
Security implications! MI5! MI6!
国外势力 国家利益
Foreign powers! National interests!
得问盟国 军方高层 中情局 北约 东盟 莫斯科
Consult our allies! Top brass! CIA, NATO, SEATO, Moscow!
莫斯科? 你没事吧 汉弗莱
Moscow Are you all right, Humphrey?
不 没有莫斯科 我不是说莫斯科
Er, no, not Moscow. I didn抰 mean Moscow.
可这消息会严重伤害在世的人
But this information could seriously damage people still alive.
要是拟合同的人还在世 他活该倒霉
The people who drew up this contract ought to be damaged!
当然 不能包庇官员 绝对的
Oh, absolutely! No question of protecting officials! Of course not!
可是主管的大臣...
But... responsible ministers...
都30年了 汉弗莱 早换了一批人了吧
It's 30 years ago. in any case, weren't the other lot in office then?
没错      你着什么急?
Well, yes... Why are you so concerned?
没有没有 跟我无关
Oh, I'm not, no, no. Not me, personally,
可事关原则 先例 政策
but it抯 the principle, the precedent, the policy...
政策归我管 汉弗莱 我说行就行 好吗?
The policy is up to me and I've said yes, so it done. Ok?
汉弗莱怎么了?
What's the matter with Humphrey?
我没犯什么错吧?
I haven't done anything wrong, have I?
不会真有安全问题吧?
There aren't any security Implications, are there?
到底搞什么?
What's the problem?
我在自言自语吗?      不 大臣 我听着呢
Am I talking to myself? No, I'm listening.
怎么不回答?
Why don't you answer?
抱歉 我以为您这是设问句
I thought your questions were purely rhetorical.
我也不明白他紧张什么
I see no reason for him to be so anxious.
除非...
Unless...
你跟我想的一样吗?      我想不会 大臣
Are you thinking what I'm thinking? I don't think so, Minister.
我什么都没在想
I'm not thinking anything, really.
我想我闻到耗子味了
I begin to smell a rat.
要我找卫生官员来吗?
Shall I get an environmental health officer?
汉弗莱在行政部干了多久?
How long has Sir Humphrey been here at Administrative Affairs?
从建部开始      那是什么时候?
Since it was founded. When was that?
1964年 就跟经济部一起...
1964. The same time they started the Department for Economic...
现在我跟您想的一样了
Now I think I'm thinking what you're thinking.
你在想什么?
And what are you thinking?
您在想 他1964年前在哪里
You're thinking, where was he before 1964?
花名册里有记载
It'll be in "Who's Who".
一定在别的部门 被网罗到行政部的
He must've been in another department and trawled for the DAA.
什么?      网罗 拿网子捞鱼
What? Trawled. Fished, caught in the net.
啊 找到了 我的天啊      怎么?
Ah, here we are. Oh, my God! What?
1950-56年 他是苏格兰事务部副主管
He was Assistant Principal at the Scottish Office.
从陆军部借调的
On secondment from the War Office.
地区合同承办官
Regional Contracts Officer.
30年前啊
30 years ago.
原来这名官员
So the official...
拱手送出4千万
who chucked away 40 million...
纳税人的钱的...
of taxpayers' money was...
真吓人
How frightful!
太可怕了 大臣      恐怖
it抯 awful, Minister. Dreadful.
所有档案几星期内就要解密了
And all the papers due for release in a few weeks' time.
叫汉弗莱马上回来
Get Humphrey to come back here at once.
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.
格拉汉 我是伯纳 大臣问汉弗莱爵士是否
The Minister wonders if Sir Humphrey could spare time
有空来开个会 几天之内
for a meeting sometime in the next few days.
马上      其实 就在今天之内
At once. In fact, sometime today is really...
马上      准确说 未来60秒之内
At once! Sometime during the next 60 seconds.
他这就过来      怎么 他没晕啊?
He's coming round now. Why? Did he faint?
不 他就...      这事很严重 伯纳
No, he's just, you know... This is serious, Bernard.
对 我知道
Yes, I know.
一点都不好笑      当然不好笑
This is no laughing matter. No, certainly not.
问题在于
The question is...
我要怎么处理呢?
how am I gong to deal with it?
依我看...      这回是设问句 伯纳
In my opinion... The question was rhetorical.
您找我 大臣?      汉弗莱 进来进来
You wanted a word, Minister? Humphrey, come in, come in.
抱歉 伯纳
Sorry, Bernard.
我在想苏格兰海岛丑闻的事
I've been thinking about this Scottish Island scandal.
真让人担心      我不觉得...
Very worrying. Well, I don't know...
你大概没意识到
You probably don't realise this,
可这责任人很可能还在做公务员
but that official could still be in the Civil Servlce.
应该不会      怎么不会?
Very unlikely. But why?
他当年大概20多岁 现在正好50多岁
He could've been in his mld-20s then, he'd be in his mld-50s now.
没准还当常任秘书了呢
Might even be a Permanent Secretary!
我真不觉得...      也是 你说的对
I hardly think... No, of course, you're right.
这么不靠谱的人怎能当常任秘书呢
Nobody who made a blunder become a Permanent Secretary.
总之我要调查到底      大臣 这种事查不到
I want an investigation. Can't find out that sort of thing.
当然查得到
Surely we can.
你说的 凡事都有记录 有档案
You said yourself that minutes are always made, records kept
在公务员系统里面
in the Civil Servlce.
现行合同的法律文件
And legal documents concerning a current contract
总不会丢掉吧
wouldn't have been thrown away.
大臣 用不用搞得这么严重呢?
Minister... aren抰 we making a little too much of this?
可能会毁掉一份光明前程 就为...
Possibly blighting a brilliant career because of a...
30年前一点小疏忽?
tiny slip 30 years ago?
反正 也没浪费很多钱嘛
After all, it抯 not such a lot of money wasted.
4千万磅?
40 million?
这个 您比比蓝光导弹
Well, not compared with Blue Streak,
TSR2轰炸机 三叉戟客机 协和飞机
TSR.2, Trident, Concorde,
政务理事会大楼
high-rise council flats,
英国铁路
British Rail,
英国利兰汽车 英国钢铁
British Leyland, British Steel,
上克莱德造船厂
Upper Clyde Shipbuilders,
原子能电站 公立综合中学
the atomic PowerStation programme, comprehensive schools,
艾塞克斯大学
the University of Essex.
对 我明白 不过它还是百倍地超出
I take your point, but it抯 still more, a hundred times more,
这名官员一辈子能挣的工资
than this official could ever have earned in his entire career.
因此我就交给你调查 找出谁干的
So I want you to look into it and find out who it was.
好吗?
Ok?
怎么了 汉弗莱?      大臣 有件事您得知道
Yes, Humphrey? There is something you ought to know.
什么 汉弗莱?
Yes, Humphrey?
被归置责任的这名官员的身份
The identity of the official whose alleged responsibility
其作出这件假定的疏忽
for this hypothetical oversight,
成为我们近来讨论的对象
as being the subject of recent discussion,
并未笼罩在密不透风的层层迷雾之中
Is not shrouded in quite such impenetrable obscurity
大异您基于早先信息作出的推断
as previous disclosures led you to assume.
一言以蔽之 追根究底
But not to put too fine a point on it...
我们讨论的这个人 也许您会吃惊
the individual in question is, It may surprise you to learn,
在您目前的谈话对象提到他时
one whom your present interlocutor...
通常会使用
Is in the habit of defining...
第一人称代词来指代
by means of the perpendicular pronoun.
你说什么?
I beg your pardon?
这人是...我
It was... I.
汉弗莱
Humphrey!
不会吧      我有压力
No? I was under pressure!
我们工作过度 慌慌张张
We were overworked, there was panic!
议会就要质询了
Parliamentary questions tabled.
显然我没受过法律训练
Obviously I'm not a trained lawyer
不然不会派我管法务部门
or I wouldn't have been in charge of the Legal Unit!
都30年了 人无完人啊
30 years ago! Everybody makes mistakes!
好了 汉弗莱 我原谅你
Well, Humphrey... I forgive you.
谢谢您 大臣
Oh, thank you, Minister.
你怎么早不告诉我 汉弗莱?
Why didn抰 you tell me about this before?
我们俩之间总没有秘密吧?
We have no secrets from each other, have we?
这得由您说 大臣      不完全由我
That is for you to say, Minister. Well, not entirely.
不过 现在要怎么办?
Anyhow, what are we gong to do?
我会被媒体轰炸的
I'm gong to be roasted
如果我不把所有文件给邮报
If I don't release all those papers to the Mall.
也许我能采取些措施...
I might be able to do something about it...
要是手头没有其他麻烦的话
If I hadn't got this other worry on my plate.
什么其他麻烦?
What other worry
还是被媒体轰炸
Being roasted by the press
因为处分全国最高效的地方政府
for disciplining the most efficient council in Great Britain.
大臣 我一直在想南德贝的事
I've been thinking about South Derbyshire.
那敢情好      显然我们动不了法律
Oh, good. Obviously we can't change the law.
不过也许可以宽大为怀
Perhaps we might show them leniency,
私下跟行政长官提一句
a private word with the Chief Executive.
给他们个机会改过
Give them a chance to mend their ways.
这应该相当有用
That might help considerably.
那我怎么跟邮报解释失踪的文件?
How will I explain the missing documents to the Mall?
这个嘛 我们有种惯用手段对付...
Well, this is what we normally do in...
这种情况
circumstances like these.
"该档案包含全部相关文件"
"This file contains the complete set of papers,
"除了极少数机密文件"
except for a number of secret documents,
"少数隶属于其他未公开档案的文件"
a few others which are part of still-active files,
"1967年洪灾中损毁的某些通信"
some correspondence lost in the floods of 1967..."
1967年冬天很恶劣吗?
Was 1967 a particularly bad winter?
不 那个冬天很不错
No, a marvellous winter.
我们丢失了无数棘手的文件
We lost no end of embarrassing files.
"运往伦敦途中遗失的某些记录"
"Records lost in the move to London,
"战争部并入国防部期间遗失的记录"
or when the War Office joined the Ministry of Defence,
"以及经正常程序抽出的报告 为了避免"
and the withdrawal of papers that could give grounds for an action
"可能引起的侵害隐私"
for libel or breach of confidence
"或冒犯友邦政府不满等情形"
or cause embarrassment to friendly governments."
貌似很情有可原嘛
Well, that's pretty comprehensive.
一般还能给他们剩下多少?
How many does that normally leave for them to look at?
实际剩下了多少?
How many does it actually leave?
大约100份? 50份?
About a hundred? Fifty?
10份? 5份?
Ten? Five?
4份?
Four?
3份? 2份?
Three? Two?
1份?
One?
0份?
Zero?
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.